-[Narrator] Welcome to Module 3 Accessible Microsoft
PowerPoint Documents. In this video, you will
learn how to make your PowerPoint documents
accessible to all learners.
In this section, we will set your document title
and language. Setting the document title in
PowerPoint is much like we did in Word. In your
PowerPoint presentation, Click File, then select
Info. From the right-hand panel, locate the
Properties section. Click on the space indicated to
the right of Title. Enter a descriptive title here,
such as "Accessible Slide Design."
To set the document language, go to the Review tab,
select Language, and choose Set Proofing Language.
From the list, select your desired language, such
as English (United States). Check the box labeled
"Do not check spelling or grammar," and then click
OK to apply your settings. Now that we have
given the title and set the preferred language for
our PowerPoint, people can understand the document
context without opening it and interpret the
content accurately. In this section, we will set
clear unique titles for each slide. Each slide
requires a different title for accurate
communication with assistive technologies. Slide
titles can be checked by selecting View from the
menu and clicking Outline View. A panel will
appear to the left of the screen, indicating the
names of each slide in the presentation, and they
appear at the top of each slide. If there is a
title duplication, it will need to be adjusted.
For instance, if two slides are titled "Common
Barriers," you could add "Part 1" and "Part 2,"
like this example here.
In this section, we will add alternative text and
create accessible hyperlinks. Images, graphs, or
charts should include alternative text or be
described as decorative. To add alternative text,
right-click on the image and select Alt Text in
the pop-up menu. The Alt Text pane will show to
the right of your screen. If the image contains
meaningful information, add alternative text in
the empty box describing the content and purpose.
In this example, the alternative text would be
"Students with disabilities drop out at about twice
the rate of their non-disabled peers." It is a best
practice to keep descriptive phrases brief. Do not
begin the description with words "Image of ..." or
"Picture of ..."; screen readers automatically use the
term "Image." If the image is simply decorative, leave
the description field box blank and check Mark as
decorative; close the Alt Text pane to apply
changes.
Microsoft PowerPoint automatically creates a
hyperlink when a URL is added to a slide. However,
to meet accessibility requirements, hyperlinks
must be clear and actionable, allowing users to
understand where the link is leading them. To add
meaningful language, right-click on the link.
Select Edit. At the top of this window, you will
enter a descriptive title such as "Visit the
Official WCAG 2.1 guidelines from W3C"
instead of "Click Here." "Visit the Official
WCAG 2.1 guidelines from W3C" alerts someone
listening to a screen reader that there is an
actionable item in the document. Designing a
visually appealing presentation can often go
against accessibility requirements. Color choice
combinations can create difficulty for users to
read text on the screen. Background and font color
should have clear contrast between them. Using a
black background with a white font works well. For
example, this due date is in a light red font on a
yellow background. These colors do not provide a
good contrast, making it difficult to read. A
suggestion would be to make the font color black
and bold and remove the background.
In this section, we will adjust font size and
fix reading order for accessibility.
Let's change some fonts. From the Slides pane on the
left side of the screen, right-click on the slide,
and select Duplicate Slide. On the new slide, delete
the top three items from the list; select all text,
and set font size to 24. Now, go to the previous
slide, and delete the bottom three items. Now,
select the remaining text from the list and set
font size to 24. Also, make sure each slide has a
unique title. This will ensure that your text is
accessible.
After setting up clear, readable text, the next
step is to verify the slides reading order.
Verifying the read order of a slide is important,
especially if additional content placeholders are
added to the slide. To check or change a slide's
reading order, in the Home tab at the top of your
screen, click Arrange and click Selection Pane.
Your Selection pane will show to the right of your
screen, listing all content found on your slide.
The screen reader will read content from bottom to
top. In this example, right now the screen reader
reads Picture 3, then Title 5, and finally
Rectangle 3. To fix this in the Selection
pane, first drag Title 5 down to the bottom;
next, place Rectangle 3 just above Title 5;
and keep Picture 3 above both objects. This
sets the correct reading order.
In this section, we will run the accessibility
checker and fix remaining issues manually.
As with all documents, accessibility should be
checked. At the top of the screen, open the Review
tab, then choose Check Accessibility. Any errors,
warnings, and tips will show in the checker on the
right side of your screen. In this example, I
still have one accessibility issue, "Missing
Slide Title". To fix it, select the error and then
choose Set as Slide Title; click Approve and the
issue will be resolved. While the PowerPoint
accessibility checker is helpful, it does not
evaluate everything. For example, it cannot verify
the font style or the size of text elements. On
Slide 6, some list items are set to 11 point
font, but the checker does not flag that. To fix
this, I will change them to 24 point. Therefore,
it is important for content creators to manually
verify appropriate font styles and sizes are used,
and that color contrast meets accessibility
standards.